Preliminary Guide to the Ruth Finlay Papers, 1960-2011 (bulk 1969-2011)
Ruth Finlay papers 1960-2011, bulk 1969-2011
Finlay, Ruth.
6.8 Linear Feet 300 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ruth Finlay Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts in 2003, 2006, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Born Ruth Ann Spencer on May 21, 1926 in Burlington, Colorado. The family lost their land in the dust bowl and relocated to Lewiston, Idaho in 1939. She married her high school sweetheart, John A. Finlay, in 1943. They later moved to South Carolina, where they spent the rest of their lives. Ruth had six sons. In 1985, she lost her larynx to cancer. She died on December 26, 2010.
Collection Overview
The first accession of the collection comprises diaries (39 volumes) written by Ruth Finlay documenting the details of and her emotional reactions to her daily life, activities, behavior, social life, and family life between 1960 and 1994. Topics include her hospitalization, ongoing treatment for, and life following cancer (1985 and onward); her relationships with her husband, children, and grandchildren; and the death of an adult son (December 1988).
The second accession (2006-0030) comprises diaries written by Finlay between January 1995 and August 2004.
The third accession (2011-0191) comprises 12 diaries written by Finlay between September 2004 and July 2010, a wedding log book, two day minders, correspondence, and family photographs.
All accessions acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Finlay, Ruth
Finlay, John A., Mrs
Finlay, John A.
Finlay family
Bereavement -- United States.
Cancer -- Patients -- United States -- Diaries
Women -- South Carolina -- Diaries
Women -- South Carolina -- Social life and customs
Family -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Family -- South Carolina -- History -- 20th century
Domestic relations -- Southern States -- History
Domestic relations -- United States -- History -- 20th century.
Motherhood -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century
South Carolina -- History.
South Carolina -- Social life and customs
Diaries
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2003-0070, 1960-1994, (3 boxes)
  - Diaries, 1960, 1969-1971, 1973-1974 (1975 laid in with 1973-1974), 1977-1982 (Box 1)
  - Diaries, 1983-1989 July (Box 2)
  - Diaries, 1989 Aug.-1994 (Box 3)
- Accession 2006-0030, 1995-2004, (5 boxes)
  - Diaries, 1995 January-2004 August (Box 1-5)
- Accessions 2011-0191 and 2011-1029, 1993-2011, (5 boxes)
  - Diaries, 2004 September-2006 March, (3 volumes) (Box 9)
  - Wedding Log Book, 1993
  - Diaries, 2006 March-2007 August, (3 volumes) (Box 10)
  - Diaries, 2007 August-2009 July, (4 volumes) (Box 11)
  - Diaries, 2009 August-2010 July, (2 volumes) (Box 12)
  - Day minders, 2009 May-2009 November, (2 volumes)
  - Emails and correspondence with Duke University regarding the Ruth Finlay Diaries, 2002-2011 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1984-1985
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1990-2009, (6 folders)